<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Ng&#39;oma Lab</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/media/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Critical conditions</title>
      <link>/project/age-hydro-ecology/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/age-hydro-ecology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In collaboration with &lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=ahv9RywAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr. Bosco Rusuwa&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Malawi,
and &lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=KC8PJlsAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr. Maggie Munthali&lt;/a&gt; based at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mwapata.mw/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MwAPata Institute&lt;/a&gt;, we will conduct a longitudinal study (over 3 years) to identify components of the environment which cue for changes in the rate of aging in natural conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A recent study addressed the question of how differential aging evolves in wild killifish colonizing ecologically different habitats. From this study, the hypothesis is that faster aging results from increased mutational loads triggered by episodes of relaxed selection, which is in agreement with evolutionary theory of aging. From a shorter-term perspective, we appreciate that water temperature increases gradually during pool desiccation, water chemistry may be more concentrated late and early in the season, and biotic factors including predation are involved. Which of these, or sub-components thereof, are critical triggers of the aging rate response?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;/media/cui_bottleneck.png&#34;&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The schematic shows how historical demographic dynamics are likely to have let to the evolution of shorter lifespans and faster aging in dryer harsher conditions. Figure: Cui et al., 2019&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We use a longitudinal study design to generate and integrate ecological and genomic time-series. In extreme climatic regions covering the range of each species, we designate at least 12 ephemeral pools of varying sizes. In these same pools, we sample components of the environment (hydro-ecological, water physico-chemical properties, benthic fauna and microbes, plant and animal communities including sources of predation). Field monitoring of these pools will proceed for a minimum of three years, with sampling at a monthly interval. Concurrently, we will estimate lifespan in the field as a proxy for the rate of aging. From these data, we will use dimension-reduction statistical methods to identify key environmental cues that correlate the most with killifish aging rates. Environmental components identified will be manipulated in more controlled conditions in a future project to dig deeper into the evolutionary dynamics of aging in natural populations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/media/mal_moz_map1.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;We will follow pools in wet vs dry regions focusing on four species in Malawi, Mozambique and Zimbabwe.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eco-Evo Genomics of aging rate in wild populations</title>
      <link>/project/age-mechs-wild/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/age-mechs-wild/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is challenging to identify and track the genetic architecture of a complex trait in a wild outbreeding population. However, it is possible to take advantage of -omic advances, traditional genetic methods, and computational tools to push this interesting frontier. In this project, we focus on the same pools sampled for environmental conditions. Thus, for each species we compare arid vs humid fish in their rate of genomic and functional changes over three years. We collect fish at three time points along the desiccation timeline to provide multiple test tissues. Using differential gene expression for arid-wet conditions, whole-genome sequencing, genome-wide association mapping (GWAS), along with functional trait measurements (changes in tissue microbiomes across season, accumulation of tissue damage indicators, and swimming performance such as fatigue and swim distance), the goal is to understand the profile of network adaptation and allele frequency variation. These data will serve as the basis for comparison with similar data sets generated in in controlled conditions. Apart from gaining insight into the ‘natural’ mechanism of differential aging in the wild, findings are expected to illuminate the problem of low corroboration of lab findings in natural populations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrating field and lab aging genomics</title>
      <link>/project/age-mechs-compgen/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/age-mechs-compgen/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Filtering eco-genomic data based on data derived from controlled experiments is a useful way to identify novel mechanisms. However, this approach asserts the superiority of a lab-based approach, which is the same way of doing things we want to vary from. A potentially better path is to attempt to input all data sets into the analysis pipeline (i.e., integration at analysis stage rather than post-analytic integration).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mechanism of aging rate in controlled conditions</title>
      <link>/project/age-mechs-lab/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/age-mechs-lab/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A major barrier to isolating genetic mechanisms for complex traits in wild populations is the difficulty to control for environmental conditions, and the out-crossed genomic landscape. To filter for candidate mechanisms with high probability of a true association with aging rate, we will rear non-lab adapted wet- vs arid-sourced fish in common garden for a few generations. The same battery of analysis performed in free-living fish will be repeated in high replication to yield a set of genes and gene networks that bear a consistent climatic signature of divergence in the aging rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/media/aquarium.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;In the lab, fish are reared in a state-of-the-art aquarium, complete with a self-cleaning technology. Image from: www.tecniplast.it.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to completely controlled experiments, semi-controlled mesocosm-based experiments will be performed to provide an intermediate scenario. We will also attempt to simulate vernal pools in our mesocosms by founding populations in large tabs seeded with sediment, transfer the tabs into a green house with tropical temperatures during the winter months, and re-wetting the tables in spring for multiple years. In the event of success with this challenging, but promising approach, the mechanisms identified should be pretty close with the natural mechanism and should provide an opportunity to filter all data sets for a high quality candidate mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/media/mesocosm_tubs.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Large tubs will be used to rear fish from late spring to early fall. A vast flat space is available for sitting of these tubs, and a greenhouse is located to the left in the image which will house simulated desiccated pools over winter months.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
